<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://shannayr.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://shannayr.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-18T02:36:33+00:00</updated><id>https://shannayr.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website: Shannay Rawal | WVU </subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/2025-02-01-Ontology-Epistemology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=""/><published>2025-02-18T02:36:33+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-18T02:36:33+00:00</updated><id>https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/2025-02-01-Ontology-Epistemology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/2025-02-01-Ontology-Epistemology/"><![CDATA[<p>Hey there, fellow Proles!</p> <p>Welcome to the fourth edition of <em>Bears, Beets, Breaking News</em>—where we dive into topics more complex than Creed’s tax returns and more fascinating than Kevin’s understanding of numbers. Today, we’re taking a break from the daily Prolefeed to explore the philosophical underpinnings of environmental engineering research.</p> <h2 id="the-research-hierarchy-from-ontology-to-methods-in-environmental-engineering">The Research Hierarchy: From Ontology to Methods in Environmental Engineering</h2> <p>As an environmental engineer engaged in stakeholder-based research, I’ve observed how the philosophical underpinnings of our work shape our approach to solving complex environmental challenges. The research hierarchy, consisting of ontology, epistemology, methodology, and methods, provides a framework for understanding these philosophical foundations and their practical applications. This edition of the newsletter attempts to map how these elements differ between quantitative and qualitative research approaches in environmental engineering.</p> <h3 id="ontology-the-nature-of-reality">Ontology: The Nature of Reality</h3> <p>At the top of the research hierarchy sits ontology, which deals with the nature of reality and what can be known about it (<i><a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3708935">Linking Ontology, Epistemology and Research Methodology</a></i>). We often adopt a realist ontology in quantitative environmental research, assuming that an objective reality exists independently of our perceptions. This might manifest in studies measuring pollutant concentrations or modeling climate change impacts. Qualitative research performed by engineers (and others without a background in social science) tends to lean towards a constructivist ontology, recognizing that stakeholders’ perceptions and social constructs play a crucial role in environmental issues. This could be attributed to experiences with NIMBY protests and construction delays. When studying community responses to proposed infrastructure projects, engineers quickly acknowledge that multiple realities coexist based on diverse stakeholder perspectives (<i><a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/209132">Alternative Ways of Seeking Knowledge in Consumer Research</a></i>).</p> <h3 id="epistemology-the-nature-of-knowledge">Epistemology: The Nature of Knowledge</h3> <p>Epistemology concerns how we acquire knowledge and the relationship between the researcher and the subject of study (<i><a href="https://us.sagepub.com/sites/default/files/upm-binaries/34087_Chapter1.pdf">An invitation to qualitative research</a></i>). Quantitative environmental research commonly aligns with a positivist epistemology, emphasizing objective measurements and the researcher’s detachment from the subject. This approach is more evident in studies without a strong human connection to the data, like research that relies on sensor data or statistical analyses of environmental trends. On the other hand, qualitative research in our field often adopts an interpretivist epistemology, recognizing the researcher’s role in interpreting stakeholder views and experiences. This is particularly relevant when conducting interviews or focus groups to understand community perceptions of environmental risks.</p> <h3 id="methodology-the-strategy-for-knowledge-creation">Methodology: The Strategy for Knowledge Creation</h3> <p>Methodology bridges our philosophical stance with practical research methods (<i><a href="https://us.sagepub.com/sites/default/files/upm-binaries/34087_Chapter1.pdf">An invitation to qualitative research</a></i>). In quantitative environmental engineering research, we often employ experimental or survey methodologies created to test hypotheses and establish causal relationships. For example, we might use controlled experiments to evaluate the effectiveness of new water treatment technologies. Qualitative methodologies in our field, such as case studies or participatory action research, aim to explore complex social-ecological systems in depth. These approaches are particularly valuable when investigating stakeholder dynamics in environmental decision-making processes (<i><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2020.02.019">Five pillars for stakeholder analyses in sustainability transformations: The global case of phosphorus</a></i>).</p> <h3 id="methods-the-tools-for-data-collection-and-analysis">Methods: The Tools for Data Collection and Analysis</h3> <p>The specific methods we use to collect and analyze data are at the base of the hierarchy. Quantitative methods in environmental engineering typically involve structured data collection techniques like surveys, measurements, or remote sensing, followed by statistical analysis. For instance, we might use air quality monitors to collect data and then apply regression analysis to identify pollution trends. On the other hand, qualitative methods often include semi-structured interviews, focus groups, or participant observation, with data analyzed through techniques like thematic analysis or grounded theory. These methods are particularly useful when exploring stakeholders’ values, beliefs, and experiences related to environmental issues (<i><a href="https://doi.org/10.29333/ajqr/14083">The Three Logics of Qualitative Research: Epistemology, Ontology, and Methodology in Political Science</a></i>).</p> <h3 id="integrating-approaches-in-stakeholder-based-research">Integrating Approaches in Stakeholder-Based Research</h3> <p>Environmental engineering projects have the potential to benefit from combining quantitative and qualitative approaches. This allows us to combine the strengths of objective measurements with rich, contextual insights from stakeholders. For example, when assessing the impacts of a proposed dam, we might use quantitative methods to model hydrological changes and qualitative methods to understand community perceptions and concerns (<i><a href="https://www.amnh.org/content/download/158575/2593966/file/stakeholder-analysis-in-environmental-and-conservation-planning.pdf">Stakeholder Analysis in Environmental and Conservation Planning</a></i>).</p> <p>More comprehensive and effective stakeholder-based environmental engineering studies can be designed by acknowledging progressive differences in the research hierarchy and their manifestation in quantitative and qualitative approaches. Adopting this approach enables us to address complex environmental challenges while considering the technical and social dimensions of sustainability.</p> <p>In the words of the immortal Michael Scott, “What is the most important thing for a company? Is it the cash flow? Is it the inventory? Nuh-uh. It’s the people. The people.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Filial Piety in the context of rural Global North communities</title><link href="https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/Filial-Piety/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Filial Piety in the context of rural Global North communities"/><published>2025-02-01T00:31:15+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-01T00:31:15+00:00</updated><id>https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/Filial-Piety</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/Filial-Piety/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to <em>Bears, Beets, Breaking News #3</em> a newsletter that explores unexpected connections faster than Jim pranks Dwight. Today, we’re diving into a nuanced exploration of social dynamics that’s more intricate than an org chart at Dunder Mifflin.</p> <p>At its core, filial piety is like an unwritten family contract of care and respect. Imagine a social agreement where younger family members are expected to honor, support, and take care of their parents and older relatives—not just out of legal obligation, but from a deep sense of gratitude and moral responsibility. It’s more than just helping mom and dad with chores or checking in occasionally; it’s about actively ensuring their well-being, respecting their wisdom, and maintaining family harmony. Think of it as a multigenerational support system where care flows both ways: parents invest in their children’s upbringing, and children later reciprocate by providing emotional, financial, and practical support as their parents age.</p> <h2 id="filial-piety-not-just-for-schrute-farms">Filial Piety: Not Just for Schrute Farms</h2> <p>You might think filial piety is just about respecting your elders and helping out on the family beet farm, but there’s more to it than that. A <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC8850268/">recent study</a> has shown that filial piety, traditionally associated with Asian cultures, has some interesting applications in rural American settings.</p> <p>The study introduces the Dual Filial Piety Model (DFPM), which breaks down filial piety into two components:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Reciprocal Filial Piety (RFP)</strong>: This is the genuine gratitude and voluntary support children give to their parents.</li> <li><strong>Authoritarian Filial Piety (AFP)</strong>: This involves obedience and fulfilling obligatory duties to parents.</li> </ul> <p>Interestingly, the research found that RFP doesn’t differ much across cultures, unlike AFP.</p> <p>This suggests that the care and support of elderly parents in rural American households might have more in common with Asian cultures than we previously thought.</p> <h2 id="from-farms-to-infrastructure-a-rural-revolution">From Farms to Infrastructure: A Rural Revolution?</h2> <p>You might wonder, “What does this have to do with my research?” Well, stick with me here. Filial piety in rural settings could be applied to how communities approach public infrastructure. In rural regions of the Global North, where centralized systems are often impractical or too expensive, the principles of filial piety could inspire a new approach:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Reciprocal Community Care</strong>: Just as children voluntarily support their parents out of gratitude, rural communities could foster a culture of voluntary maintenance and improvement of local infrastructure.</li> <li>&lt;/strong&gt;Shared Responsibility&lt;/strong&gt;: The authoritarian aspect of filial piety could translate into a more structured system of community duties for maintaining public systems.</li> <li>Imagine a world where managing a septic system is as ingrained in rural culture as helping out on the family farm. It's not quite as exciting as a Dundies award ceremony, but it could revolutionize how we approach rural infrastructure.</li> </ul> <p>That’s all for now, folks! Remember, in the words of the great philosopher Michael Scott,<br/></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Filial-Piety-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Filial-Piety-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Filial-Piety-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Filial-Piety.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>So, let’s aim high in how we care for our communities and infrastructure!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Bears, Beets, Breaking News"/><category term="Behavioral"/><category term="Sustainability"/><category term="Community"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Advancing Climate action in the rural Global North]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Doughnut Economics</title><link href="https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/Doughnut-Economics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doughnut Economics"/><published>2025-01-25T00:32:13+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-25T00:32:13+00:00</updated><id>https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/Doughnut-Economics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://shannayr.github.io/blog/2025/Doughnut-Economics/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to <em>Bears, Beets, Breaking News #2</em> —your favorite sporadic newsletter, as unpredictable as a Dunder Mifflin staff meeting. Today, we’re diving into a topic more complex than Michael Scott’s management style: <strong>Doughnut Economics</strong>.</p> <h2 id="doughnut-economics-a-framework-for-sustainable-development">Doughnut Economics: A Framework for Sustainable Development</h2> <p>Doughnut Economics, introduced by <a href="https://www.kateraworth.com/doughnut/">Kate Raworth</a> in 2012 <d-cite key="raworth2012"></d-cite>, is a novel approach to economic thinking that balances human needs with planetary boundaries. This model, visually represented as a Doughnut, consists of two concentric rings:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Inner Ring</strong>: The social foundation, encompassing essential human needs such as health, education, and gender equality.</li> <li><strong>Outer Ring</strong>: The ecological ceiling, based on the planetary boundaries framework developed by the Stockholm Resilience Centre. This identifies nine critical Earth system processes that maintain planetary stability and resilience.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Shortfalls and overshoot in the Doughnut <d-cite key="Raworth2017"></d-cite> <em>Source: The Lancet Planetary Health</em></p> <h3 id="the-safe-and-just-space-for-humanity">The Safe and Just Space for Humanity</h3> <p>Between these two rings lies the “safe and just space for humanity,” where human needs are met without overshooting Earth’s ecological limits. Unlike traditional economic models that prioritize unlimited growth, Doughnut Economics advocates for creating <strong>regenerative and distributive economies</strong> that thrive within planetary boundaries.</p> <h3 id="seven-ways-to-think-like-a-21st-century-economist">Seven Ways to Think Like a 21st-Century Economist</h3> <p>Doughnut Economics proposes seven key principles to guide modern economic thinking:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Doughnut-Economics2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p><a href="https://www.opendemocracy.net/en/transformation/seven-ways-to-think-like-21st-century-economist/">Seven ways to think like a 21st-century economist</a> <em>Source: Doughnut Economics Action Lab</em><d-cite key="RaworthBook"></d-cite></p> <p>This framework has gained traction internationally, influencing discussions across education, communities, businesses, and governments. Its holistic approach offers a promising path toward achieving sustainable development while respecting social and ecological boundaries.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-doughnuts-secret-recipe-three-pillars-of-sustainability">The Doughnut’s Secret Recipe: Three Pillars of Sustainability</h2> <p>The three pillars of sustainability—<strong>environmental, social, and economic</strong>—are baked right into the Doughnut Economics model. The goal is to find balance and create systems that work harmoniously across these interconnected domains.</p> <hr/> <p>That’s all for now, folks! Remember, in the words of the great philosopher Michael Scott, <em>“I’m not superstitious, but I am a little stitious.”</em></p> <p>For more information on Doughnut Economics, visit <a href="https://doughnuteconomics.org/about-doughnut-economics">Doughnut Economics Action Lab</a>. To learn about the planetary boundaries framework that informs the Doughnut’s ecological ceiling, check out the <a href="https://www.stockholmresilience.org/research/planetary-boundaries.html">Stockholm Resilience Centre</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Bears, Beets, Breaking News"/><category term="Economics"/><category term="Sustainability"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An overview of the Doughnut Economics framework]]></summary></entry></feed>